<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Acts and statutes set downe by the Committee of Estates of Scotland; for regulating the matter of excise, and speedy bringing in of the moneyes to be raised thereupon: conforme to the power given to them by the Convention of Estates.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1161C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203526</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52612238</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52612238</idno>
            <idno type="VID">179542</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 179542)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2793:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Acts and statutes set downe by the Committee of Estates of Scotland; for regulating the matter of excise, and speedy bringing in of the moneyes to be raised thereupon: conforme to the power given to them by the Convention of Estates.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Parliament. Committee of Estates.</author>
                  <author>Primrose, Archibald, Sir, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 9 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed Evan Tyler, Printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Headpiece; initial letter.</note>
                  <note>With marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Dated on page 1: At Edinburgh the 15. of February 1644.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Arch. Primerose.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Excise tax --  Law and legislation --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:179542:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:179542:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ACTS AND STATUTES Set downe by the COMMITTEE OF ESTATES OF <hi>SCOTLAND; For regulating the matter of</hi> EXCISE, <hi>and ſpeedy bringing in of the moneyes to be raiſed thereupon: Conforme to the power given to them by the</hi> CONVENTION <hi>of</hi> ESTATES.</p>
            <p>EDINBURGH: <hi>Printed by</hi> Evan Tyler, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:179542:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:179542:2"/>
            <head>At Edinburgh the <hi>15.</hi> of February <hi>1644.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Orſameikle as the Eſtates of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome finding it neceſſary that ſome means ſhould be provided for ſettling a ſtocke of credit or ſecuritie, whereupon moneyes may be raiſed for ſupplying the neceſſities of the Armies ſent from this Kingdome into England and Ireland, did by their Act of the laſt of Januarie unanimouſly agree and ordaine that the ſame ſhould be by way of Exciſe, and recommended to the Committee of Eſtates to take the beſt way how the ſame might be moſt ſpeedily and with leaſt expence managed and uplifted; And the Committee of Eſtates having taken the ſame to their conſideration, they have thought fit, and accordingly concluded and agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Acts following, as moſt conducing to the better regulating and uplifting of the moneyes to be raiſed on this Exciſe; And ordains the ſame to be printed, and publiſhed at the Market Croſſes and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Kirks of the Kingdome, wherethrough none pretend ignorance of the ſame.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of which Acts the tenor followes.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</note>THe Committee of Eſtates think fit, that for the better ordering of this Exciſe there ſhould be a Commiſſion ſettled to have the charge thereof, And for that purpoſe nominate and appoint <hi>John</hi> Earle of Lauderdale, <hi>John</hi> Lord Balmerino, and <hi>Robert</hi> Lord Burgh-<hi>lie,</hi> Sir <hi>Patrick Hammiltoun,</hi> Sir <hi>Michael Balfoure</hi> of Denmylne, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>James Reid</hi> of Pitlethie, Sir <hi>John Smith</hi> Proveſt of Edinburgh, <hi>John Semple</hi> Proveſt of Dumbartan, and <hi>James Stuart</hi> Merchant in Edinburgh, or any three of them, and the Lord Chancellour to be ſupernumerarie, to be Commiſſioners of Exciſe; With power to them to governe the whole office of Exciſe, To make Acts and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions for the better regulating thereof, and the more ſpeedy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifting of moneyes to be raiſed thereupon, and to ſee the ſame put in execution: With power alſo to them, To nominate, appoint, cenſure, or diſplace, as they ſhall finde occaſion, all ſubordinate Officers, as Collectors, Surveyers, Keepers of the Regiſters of Entries and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, and all other ſubſervient Officers: and at their entries to take
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:179542:3"/>their oathes and ſurety for the faithfull diſcharge of their offices, and to allow them ſuch yearly and proportionable allowances for their paines, as they with approbation of the Committee of Eſtates ſhall think fitting.</p>
               <p>As alſo with power to them, To call to an account, als oft as they ſhall think ſitting, the Theſaurer of Exciſe, Collectors, Surveyers, and others Intrometters; And to keep in record all the moneyes and entries that ſhall come into the Office, to be repreſented by them to the Eſtates or their Committees, as the ſame ſhall be called for; And generally with power to them to doe every thing that may tend for the right regulating of this Exciſe, and to give their oathes <hi>de fideli ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtratione.</hi> This Commiſſion to endure ay and while it be recalled by the Eſtates or their Committees, to whom the Commiſſioners are to be anſwerable for their proceedings.</p>
               <p>Likeas the Committee of Eſtates nominates and appoints <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap> to be Theſaurer of this Exciſe,<note place="margin">Theſaurer.</note> With power to him and his ſervant or under-Receiver, for whom he ſhall be anſwerable, to receive the whole moneyes of Exciſe from all the Collectors thereof, and to disburſe the ſame as he ſhall receive warrant from the Eſtates or their Committees, without whoſe warrant he is to disburſe nothing, except the ordinary allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and other incident neceſſaries belonging to the office, as hee ſhall be warranted by the Commiſſioners of Exciſe: And the The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurer is hereby appointed to make and deliver a faithfull and true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all receits and disburſements to the Commiſſioners or <hi>Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi> thereof monethly, or oftner, as he ſhall be required by the Eſtates or their Committees, and ſhall give his oath and finde caution for the faithfull account and diſcharge of his Office.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Regiſters and Clerks</note>It is alſo ordained, That there be a Regiſter belonging to the Office, who ſhall keepe a booke wherein are to be inſert all the receits of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes raiſed upon this Exciſe (being allowed by the Commiſſioners) according as the ſame ſhall be given up by the ſeverall Collectors in Burghs and other places in the Countrey: Wherein alſo are to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the names and ſurnames of the Collectors thereof, and of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall places and Pariſhes whereout of theſe ſummes were colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, with the date of the deliverie thereof to the Theſaurer. As alſo all extracts that the ſurveyors ſhall take out of any note or booke belonging to the Cuſtome-houſes, and entries to be made by the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyors of Exciſable goods, remaining in Cellars, Store-houſes, or any other places or houſes of any perſons that ſels, buyes, or ſpends any of theſe Commodities.</p>
               <p>And this is to be without prejudice of the Office of Clerke to the Exciſe and his deputes, who are to minute and frame all acts and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants that comes before the Commiſsioners, or iſſueth from them, and keep a Regiſter thereof, write Miſsives, and doe every other thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent to the Office of a Clerk.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Collectors.</note>The Collectors are to receive and levy money of all Exciſable
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:179542:3"/>goods, within the bounds appointed to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>. And to receive from the Surveyers of theſe bounds, the Inventar of Exciſable Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, conforme to the Survey: or they themſelves may enquire and take up the Exciſe as they ſhall think beſt for the Service. The Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors of the Shires of Edinburgh, Lithgow, Haddinton, Berwick, Roxburgh, Peebles, Lanerick, Stirlin, Perth, Fyffe, Forfar, Clack-mannan, and Kinroſſe, ſhall the ſecond Tueſday of March next, come to the office of Exciſe, and bring in the Exciſe money payed the moneth before; they ſhall enter the ſame in the book of office, and then by warrant deliver them to the Theſaurer. Upon the ſecond Tueſday of April, the Collectors of the Shires of Renfrew, Dum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartan, Argyle, Tarbet, Bute, Air, Dumfreis, Stuartie of Kircudbright, Wigton, Kincardin, Aberdene, and Bamff, ſhall do the like ſince the tenth of February. And upon the ſecond Tueſday of May, the Collectors of the Shires of Murray, Innerneſſe, Nairne, Sutherland, Cromartie, Caithneſſe, Orknay, and Zetland, ſhall do the like ſince the tenth of February laſt. And the Collectors are to do every other thing as they ſhall be warranted by the Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>The Surveyers are hereby authorized and warranted;<note place="margin">Surveyers.</note> To enter the Cuſtome-houſes, ſearch, view, examine, take Copies of any Cuſtome and Impoſt book belonging thereto; As alſo to enter the Sellers, Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, Brew-houſes, or any other houſes or places belonging to any perſons, that ſels, buyes, or ſpends, any of the ſaids Commodities lyable to Exciſe: And to take Inventar thereof, for rhe Collectors uſe in leavying the Exciſe money. They are alſo to perform this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as they ſhall be commanded by the Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Subſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent officers.</note>The Subſervient officers, are hereby authorized with power, To make ſeach for un-exciſed goods, and of all thoſe who ſhall refuſe to make true entrie of their Exciſable Commodities: And to ſummond offenders before the Commiſſioners: And to do any other thing competent to ſuch offices, as they ſhall be warranted by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ale and Beer.</note>And that their Officers may the more readily performe their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall charges, and the Exciſe money timouſly lifted; It is ſtatute and ordained, That all Importers, or Brewers of Beer to Burgh or Land, for ſale, or private uſe within this Kingdome, ſhall weekly deliver to the Collector of Exciſe or Surveyer, a true and perfect Liſt of the Beer weekly brewed, or imported by them as ſaid is. And that they pay the Exciſe to the Collector weekly, and the Brewer for private uſe monethly: And both are to give up an accompt, and make payment as aforeſaid, under the pain of forfeit of the double of the Beer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; beſide, That the Brewer or Importer for ſale, ſhall be diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Trade for a year thereafter; And this failzie to be proven by any lawfull manner of probation.</p>
               <p>And it is declared, That the Exciſe of Ale and Wine ſhall be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifted, according to the ſeverall Rates in the Table of Exciſe, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to every Boll of browne Malt, containing foure Furlots of prik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met, within the Kingdome, fifteene gallons of Ale; and to every
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:179542:4"/>Tunne of Wine ſixtie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> gallons. And it is ordained, That the buyer of Ale, Beer, or any other Merchandiſe exciſable and retailed, ſhall notwithſtanding of the truſt of the ſtock, be obliged to pay the Exciſe in ready money.</p>
               <p>It is ordained that all Malt-men in Burgh or Land, ſhall keep a book, wherein ſhall be inſert all the Bols of Malt made by them, and the names of all the buyers thereof, with the quantity ſold to every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and what quantity they brew themſelves, and which book or double thereof, the ſaid Malt-man ſhall deliver under his hand to the office of Exciſe Collectors or Surveyers, when he ſhall be required; and failing herein, he ſhall confiſcate all his Malt concealed and not given up as ſaid is.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is ordained, That all Millers ſhall declare and give up to the Collectors and Surveyers as they ſhall be required, of all the Malt, ground at their ſeverall and reſpective Milnes every week, under all higheſt pain, and as they will be anſwerable to the Commiſſioners of Exciſe.</p>
               <p>Whereas a great quantity of Malt is uſually tranſported to the farre High-Lands; It is ordained, That the buyers and tranſporters ſhall pay the Exciſe to the ſellers thereof, notwithſtanding they buy the ſame upon truſt, and take a ticket of payment of the Exciſe, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing produced to the Collector or Surveyer where they live, ſhall be freed of the Exciſe, otherwiſe ſhall pay the Exciſe, and forfeit the whole Malt concealed.</p>
               <p>It is alſo ordained,<note place="margin">Wine.</note> That the Cuſtome and Impoſt books, be made patent to the Surveyers, or other Officers of Exciſe, who are ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to take a note of the ſame, and of the Wines entred therein; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, That the Merchant-Venturers or Owners, ſhall be obliged to declare to whom he hath ſold the ſame, Vintner or other perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever; and what they ſell for private uſe, that the firſt Seller or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter ſhall be lyable for the Exciſe thereof, which is to be payed in by the buyer for private uſe to them before the delivery thereof; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Wine it ſelf is taken upon truſt. And for ſuch Wines as the Merchant-Venturer hath before this time ſold and delivered for private uſe; It is ordained, That the buyer or receiver ſhall be obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to give up an accompt thereof to the Collector or Surveyer of the Exciſe, and pay the Exciſe thereof; As alſo that the Vintner give up a weekly accompt to the Collector or Surveyer what they ſell, and pay Exciſe accordingly: Wherein if either the buyer of Wine for private uſe, or the Vintner ſhall failzie, they are to forfault the double availe of the Wine, concealed and not payed for; Beſides, That the Vintner ſhall be diſcharged ſale of Wine for a year. And this failzie to be proven as of before.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aquavitae and ſtrong Waters.</note>That all makers and ſellers of Strong-waters and Aquavitae, give up atrue Inventar under their hands to the office of Exciſe, or to the Collectors and Surveyers of the bounds where they dwell, as they ſhal be required, of all the Strong waters &amp; Aquavitae made by them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be ſold; &amp; after it is ſold, give up a Liſt of the firſt buyers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:179542:4"/>with the quantity ſold to every perſon; to the effect the Exciſe may be tried and payed to the publick. And it is declared, That the maker or ſeller of the ſaids Strong-waters, ſhall pay the Exciſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they be ſold, and take the Exciſe from the firſt buyer. And if the maker or ſeller failzie to give the ſaid Inventar or Liſt, or if the ſamine ſhall be improven according to the Laws of the Countrey, the ſaid maker or ſeller ſhal for fault the value of the Strong-waters ſo concealed and improven. Likeas the firſt buyers of Strong-waters for ſale, ſhall give an accompt of all the Strong-waters and Aquavitae lying in their hands as yet unſold, and of what they have ſold, after the tenth of February inſtant, to the Collectors or Surveyers within their bounds: To the intent what is ſold after the ſaid day, may pay Exciſe; and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling herein, to for fault the value of the waters not compted and Exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And the maker or ſeller paying the Exciſe, ſhall give a ticket to every other ſeller of the ſaid Strong-waters, teſtifying that the Exciſe is payed, and whoſo ſhall not inſtruct the payment of Exciſe by the ticket foreſaid, ſhall be lyable in paiment of the Exciſe, and for fault the value of the waters not exciſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Merchant Wares.</note>And whereas it is the cuſtome of all Merchant Ware exciſed, That at the receiving of their Goods, they make Entrie to the Office of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and pay the Exciſe before they retail the ſame: Or otherwayes that the Surveyers enter their Shops, Ware-houſes, or ſuch other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where their Goods may be apprehended, and take oaths for help and qualification, and confiſcate the double of what is concealed for the firſt fault; Yet notwithſtanding, for the eaſe and better accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modating the Merchants Traders with Exciſed Goods in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; It is ordained, that the Retailers and Sellers of Goods charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able with Exciſe, ſhall monethly give in to the Commiſſioners of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, or any having their warrant, a Book ſubſcribed by their hands, containing a note and an accompt of all the ſeverall Goods and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities Exciſeable and ſold by them within that moneth, with the dayes of the moneth, and perſons names to whom they were ſold, and pay the Exciſe accordingly. And the failzie or omiſſion herein, to be the triple of the price of the Commodities omitted or concealed, and to be proven as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And it is ordained, that all Exciſable Commodities that are bought by a Shop-keeper or Retailer from another, the firſt Retailer or Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper is lyable in payment of the Exciſe. Alſo whatſoever Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities are bought by others then Shop-keepers, for private uſe from the Importer, the Importer or firſt Seller is lyable for Exciſe. And whatſoever Commodities are bought from any Importer, by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Burger in any other Burghs, or by any Merchant that keeps Booth, the firſt Buyer from the Importer payes the Exciſe in the place where he lives. And therefore it is hereby declared, that the firſt Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter is onely lyable to pay the Exciſe of thoſe Goods he ſells to any that have no reſidence within Burgh, or Chapmen that have no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant reſidence, but travells with his Pack thorow the Countrey. And therefore upon the Importers certificat of the firſt payment of Exciſe, theſe parties are free.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:179542:5"/>
               <p>It is alſo ordained,<note place="margin">Fleſhes.</note> That the Deacons of Fleſhers within Burgh, or any Fleſher elſwhere, ſhall give up the names of all the Maſters of their Calling, and the names of all thoſe that preſenteth Fleſhes to be ſold in Markets: And that every Maſter ſhall give up the names of all their Servants and Slayers; And that the Fleſhers and Slayers of Oxen, Bulls, or any ſlaughtered Goods, mentioned in the cable of Exciſe in Edinburgh, Leith, Cannongate, or Liberties thereof; Potterraw, Weſt-port, or Pleaſance, ſhall compeir on Monday of every week before the Commiſſioners of Exciſe, beginning the fourth Munday of February, the 26. day of the Moneth: Bringing with them a Liſt of all the ſlaughtered and ſold Goods from the tenth of February, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they may pay the Exciſe thereof; And failing of compearance or paying the Exciſe, they ſhall forfeit the price of each Beaſt concealed, <hi>toties quoties;</hi> And failing thereof, ſhall be impriſoned, till they make payment of all by-gone Exciſes and forfeitures unpayed: as alſo finde caution for their appearance and paying of Exciſes and forfeits they ſhall incurre in time coming, and be diſcharged of that Calling, during the pleaſure of the Commiſſioners of Exciſe.</p>
               <p>It is alſo ordained, that every Porter, or any other that ſhal be appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within Burgh, ſhall keep a Book, to be given in under their ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and declaration to the Commiſſioners, wherein ſhall be inſert the number and ſeverall kindes of all Exciſeable Beaſts, both ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and unſlaughtered, that entereth within the Ports thereof, with the names of the perſons to whoſe behoof thoſe Beaſts are brought in. And the ſaid Porter, or other appointed, ſhall receive the Exciſe of the ſlaughtered Goods from the in-bringer thereof, not ſhewing a ticket from the Surveyer, that it is already payed; otherwayes he ſhall take the Exciſe, and give a ticket to warrant him at all other Surveyers hands, and deliver the ſame to the Collector. And whoſoever buyeth Skinnes or Hides of ſlaughtered Goods within Burgh, ſhall keep a Book to be given in under his ſubſcription and declaration, wherein ſhall be inſert the names of the Fleſhers, and ſellers of the Skinnes and Hides within the ſaids Burghs, that the more exact triall may be had of all the ſlaughtered Goods therein, leſt the Publicke be defrauded of the benefit of the ſame. And if the ſaids Buyers of Skinne and Hide neglect to bring in this Book monethly, and oftner as they ſhall be required, they ſhall forfeit all the Skinnes they have coſt and not given up; and this concealment to be proven, <hi>ut ſupra:</hi> and the like or any other courſe ſhall be taken by the Commiſſioners for the reſt of the Kingdom in Burgh or Land. The Exciſe of Fleſhes is to be payed by the Slayer or Fleſher for ſale; And ſiclike by any that have of their own, whether payed by their Tenants, or of their own pleniſhing.</p>
               <p>Touching Tobacco, It is ordained, that all the Cuſtome and Impoſt Books be patent to the Office of Exciſe,<note place="margin">Tobacco.</note> or to the Collectors and Surveyors, to the intent an entrie may be known for the Exciſe; And that all Skippers, Mariners, and Owners of Tobacco, are obliged before they put out any Goods out of their Ships and Veſſels, to make
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:179542:5"/>a true entrie thereof under their ſubſcription, and upon declaration, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pain of confiſcation of what is concealed. And that they give up an Inventar of all the Tobacco Imported in their Ships or Veſſels, with the names of the Owners thereof; and that no takſman ſhall take entrie of other Goods, till the whole Tobacco be entred: to the effect it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſold, the Exciſe may be payed to the Publick, for which the ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhall be lyable; and ſhall keep a book, which under their hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing, and upon declaration, they ſhall produce to the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Collectors, or Surveyers as they ſhall be required; in which book ſhall be inſert the names and ſir-names of all the buyers, with the quantitie bought by every one.</p>
               <p>And it is ordained, That the firſt ſeller of Tobacco ſhall give a ticket to every buyer, ſhewing the Exciſe thereof payed to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: And if the buyer cannot inſtruct payment of the Exciſe by this ticket; he is to be lyable in payment of the Exciſe by and attour the confiſcation of his Tobacco.</p>
               <p>And for tryall of all Tobacco already imported, and yet unfold within the Kingdome; It is ordained, that Shop-keepers, Taverners, Ale-ſellers, or other ſellers of Tobacco whatſoever, ſhall be obliged to give a true Inventar and accompt of all the Tobacco lying in their hands, or what they have ſold, after the tenth of February, to the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Exciſe, or to the Collectors and Surveyers within the bounds where they dwell. Which if they delay, till ſearch and triall be made thereof, they ſhall be lyable to the double of the Exciſe by and attour the confiſcation of the Tobacco. And it is ordained that all Skippers, Mariners, or Owners of Tobacco, when they make entry of the ſame, ſhall finde caution to make payment of the Exciſe after the ſale there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Coal tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</note>It is ordained, That all Coale-Maſters be obliged to cauſe their Grieves at the loading of any Ship or other Veſſell with Coale, to be tranſported out of the Kingdome, keep a book, wherein ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert the juſt price of the loading of the ſaid Ship or Veſſell, with the name of the Ship, Maſter or Skipper, and date of loading, which book or double thereof he ſhall give up under his hand-writing to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector or Surveyer, the firſt Tueſday of every moneth, beginning the firſt Tueſday of March next to come, for the Exciſe payable after the tenth of February before: As alſo the Maſter and Owner of the Coale, ſhall upon his honour and credit, ſubſcribe the book foreſaid, that it is juſt and right to their beſt knowledge. And failing of the giving up of the ſaid Inventar, and paying of the Exciſe thereof, the Maſter and Owner of the Coale ſhall pay the triple of the concealed Coale.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bestiall tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note>It is ordained, That all Tackſmen of the Cuſtomes on the Borders, for the Beſtiall driven into England, ſhall keep a book, and give in the ſame under their ſubſcription &amp; true declaration to the office of Exciſe, wherein ſhall be inſert the number and ſeverall kinde of beaſts, with the names of the Drovers, and dayes of the moneth when they paſſe; and ſhall be comptable for the Exciſe thereof foure times in the year and oftner, as they ſhall be required. And failing of their compea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:179542:6"/>compting and paying, ſhall forfeit the triple of the Exciſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ale and Beer tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</note>It is ſtatute and ordained, That no Brewers, ſellers of Ale or Beer, give any Beer or Ale to Skippers for proviſion of their Ships, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Skipper deliver to them a Warrant and Licence for the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the ſame from the Collector or Surveyer within the bounds where they load their Ships, or (in their abſence) of the Magiſtrate of the bounds, to the intent they take in no more Beer nor Ale under that pretext, nor may be judged ſufficient for the voyage. And in caſe of the deliverie of any Beer or Ale, without the Warrant fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, the ſaids Brewers or Sellers ſhall pay the double of the Exciſe of all Beer and Ale, ſo and without Warrant delivered by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Made work imported, which is the explanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nult Act contained within the printed Table of Exciſe.</note>It is ordained, That all kinde of made Work, brought home and ſold, <hi>viz.</hi> Braſſe-Chandlers, Spurres, Bridle-bits, Stirrop-irons, Horſe-combs, Knives, mounted-Swords above ten marks, or Guards above the ſame price. All manner of Sadles, Sadle and Horſe-graith, Goldſmith-Work of all ſorts of Plate, Rings, Jewels ſet or un-ſet. All forreine Pewter, Hangings, Tapeſtrie, mounted Beds, Stools, Chaires, Cuſhions, Carpets, Blankets, Rugs, Coverings, Feather-beds, Cods, Bowſters, Quilts, Trunks, Chamber-ſtools, Hat-caſes, Caves, Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, and Cloak-bags, Gloves and Purſes of all kind. All made Work of Holland, Cambrick, Lawne, Tiffanie plain or laced, Needle or Cut-Work, Muffs, Fannes, Feathers, Pokes, Embroidered Caps and Slip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers or with Lace, drinking Glaſſes, wrought Petticots; and Waſcots, Clocks, Watches, and Munters, Boots and Shooes, ſhall be given up by the Merchants-ſellers thereof, under ſubſcription and declaration to the Commiſſioners, Collectors, or Surveyers, and pay the Exciſe thereof for every twelve pound value 13. ſhillings 4. pence: And failing of giving up, or paying the Exciſe, to forfeit the worth of the Goods concealed.</p>
               <p>The Committee of Eſtates, Ordaines the Commiſſioners of every Pariſh, and Collectors of the bounds joyntly, to appoint the Surveyers, to take ſufficient caution of them, and adminiſter to them the oath for faithfull adminiſtration. And the Surveyer ſhall give in their weekly or monethly accompts to the Commiſſioners of every Pariſh, who ſhall ſubſcribe the ſame joyntly with the Surveyer, and upon their credit and honour to their beſt knowledge, teſtifie the truth of the ſaids accompts; to the intent there may be a true charge to the Collectors of Exciſe: And alſo that the Collectors ſhall give in the double of the Surveyers book ſo ſubſcribed with their own books un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands and declaration to the Commiſſioners, that the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts of moneys therein contained are juſt and true.</p>
               <p>If any perſon or perſons, liable in payment of Exciſe, ſhall refuſe, conceale, or neglect to pay the ſame, according to the rates contained in the table of Exciſe, or doe any thing contrary thereto, the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proven before the Commiſſioners, they ſhall forfeit the triple of the value of the goods or commodities ſo by him concealed or not payed: And the Commiſsioners hath hereby power to give order for
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:179542:6"/>poynding the readieſt of the offenders goods, and commit them to priſon till they pay the forfeit; And that the Informer ſhall have payed him from the Theſaurer, which ſhall be allowed him, the third part of any forfeits that ſhall accreſſe by his information. And it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that all confiſcate goods, fines, forfeits, and penalties, taken by the Collectors or Surveyors, or other Officers, ſhall be payed to the office of Exciſe, with the Exciſe moneyes payable by them, the ſame confiſcate goods and penalties being inſert in a book, with the names off whom they were taken, and for what cauſes; which booke they ſhall give into the office under their hand, and upon declaration, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the third part to the Informer, as is aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>The Commiſsioners of Exciſe have hereby power and authority to call before them any perſon or perſons they ſhall thinke fit, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme and teſtifie touching all and every one of the ſaids ordinances in the Exciſe, and to examine any perſons upon oath for the better diſcoverie of any fraud or neglect in the not entring of any commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to be entred, or not paying the Exciſe, conforme to the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces made thereanent; Which oath the Commiſsioners, or any they ſhall appoint by their hand-writings, ſhall have power to adminiſter, and the teſtimony of two credible witneſſes to be ſufficient in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe.</p>
               <p>It is hereby ordained, that all Commiſsioners, Theſaurers, Clerks; Regiſters, Collectors, Surveyors, or other Officers of Exciſe, and all other perſon or perſons who ſhall do any thing in execution or perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of any ordinance of the ſaid office, ſhall be therein from time to time protected and ſaved harmeleſſe by the power and authority of the Eſtates and their Committees.</p>
               <p>Like as all Proveſts and Bailies within Burghs, Sheriffes, Stewarts, Bailies, Conſtables, and their deputes, and other Magiſtrates to Burgh and Land, and all Colonels and Committees of warre in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, for the time, are hereby commanded and ordained, to be aiding and aſsiſting to the ſaids Commiſsioners and Officers of Exciſe, and every one of them, in the execution of their ſeverall offices and articles therein contained; and that they have a ſpeciall care that the Exciſe of Beere and Ale, Wines, Fleſhes, and other things, be duely payed, and the refuſers puniſhed, according to the Statutes in that behalfe made: And hereby they faile not, as they will be anſwerable to the Eſtates; or their Committees.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Arch. Primeroſe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
